Finding Aid for the Tulancingo (Hildago, Mexico) Manuscript Collection, 1567-1882 LSC.2073
UCLA Library Special Collections
Tulancingo (Hildago, Mexico) Manuscript Collection
1567-1882
UCLA Library Special Collections
Grepe, John H.
LSC.2073
4 linear feet (8 boxes)
This collection consists of manuscript documents in Spanish and Nahuatl from the town of Tulancingo (Hidalgo, Mexico). The documents consist primarily of civil litigation case files, but also include a small amount of criminal case files and several government printed broadsides.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942327973606533
Biography
This collection of manuscripts was in the private collection of John H. Grepe of Dallas, Texas from approximately 1957 to 1975. In September 1975, Grepe sold the items as one collection to Gene Hanrahan, president of R & D Books of Salisbury, North Carolina. In August 1977, this same collection was sold via Libros Latinos of Los Angeles, California to the University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA). In August 1981, more Tulancingo manuscripts were acquired by UCLA from Howard Karno Books, Inc. and added to the collection.
This collection was formerly known as the John H. Grepe collection and A Collection of material about Tulancingo, Hidalgo, Mexico, 1540-1875.
Scope and Content
Collection consists primarily of civil litigation case files from the district of Tulancingo, Mexico, dating from 1567-1882. The collection is interspersed with a few criminal case files and several government printed broadsides. Some case files also fall under the jurisdiction of Mexico City.
The boxes have been roughly divided according to the date of judgment or arbitration date; however, many files include subsequent notations entered by civil authorities as it related to outstanding matters towards fulfillment of the judgment.
Case files prior to 1837 are notable for revealing the maneuverings of indigenous communities within the legal system, the involvement of women in various business and property disputes, the colonial tribute system, tensions surrounding the War of Independence, and acts of resistance to the colonial regime by native peoples. Some of the more interesting case files include a property dispute involving Martín Cortés, the son of Hernán Cortés, the investigation of an Indian riot, and an Indian woman, who had been a traditional healer, being accused of witchcraft. Case files prior to 1837 contain some documents in Nahuatl.
Case files from 1846 to 1882 deal primarily with probate matters (often including estate inventories and wills), financial disputes between merchants and creditors, and demands for repayment of liens or mortgages. Researchers will find extensive documents with respect to four different actions: probate matters pertaining to the estate of Maria Josefa Ortega, a bankruptcy proceeding against Apolonio Uribarri, a civil dispute involving the Sanchez Hidalgo family, and the dissolution of a commercial partnership involving Spanish merchants Antonio Gayol and Tomas Urrutia. Scholars interested in researching issues of gender and sexuality will find several notable cases, for example, a case involving an older male resident who pursued relations with a younger girl and later denied paternity to their child; cases of mothers seeking legal recognition and assets from the fathers of illegitimate children; and cases involving allegations of physical abuse and infidelity. In addition to the aforementioned, scholars will find numerous examples of women's involvement in civil disputes over outstanding mortgages, as business owners, as estate executors and legal guardians for their children, and in property disputes. Case files from this period contain very little mention of Indian peoples and no Nahuatl documents.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Printed materials (.5 box)
Pre-1837 manuscripts (2.5 boxes)
Post-1852 manuscripts (5 boxes).
Related Material
Byron McAfee papers, ca. 1553-1964 (Collection 339). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Eduard Seler papers, ca. 1884-1922 (Collection 1449). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Collection of material relating to Mexico, 1860-1930 (Collection 190). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Tulancingo (Hildalgo, Mexico) Manuscript Collection (14 items).
Tulancingo (Hidalgo, Mexico) -- History -- Sources.; Tulancingo (Hidalgo, Mexico) -- Trials, litigation, etc. -- Archives.; Nahuatl language-Texts.; Indians of Mexico -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- History -- Sources.; Grepe, John H.--Former owner.
- Printed materials, 1743-1799; .5 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Series consists of broadsides and printed religious material.
  - Broadsides, 1743; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Broadsides, 1760-1769; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Broadsides, 1780-1789; 8 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Broadsides, 1790-1799; 13 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Religious printed material, ca. 1792-3; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Bula de composicion para los Reynos de Indias."
- Pre-1837 manuscripts, ca. 1567-1837; 2.5 boxes
  Series consists of civil and criminal litigation documents, including some in Nahuatl.
  - [Compilation of petitions], ca. 1567 - 1573 January 2; 58 leaves: paper; 33 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Anachronistic compilation of petitions, sewn together. Most were presented to the alcalde mayor (chief magistrate), Don Pedro Ladron de Guevara. Documents primarily concern economic or material redress and reference the districts of Singuilucan, Acatlán.
  - [Documents relating to the Sebastian Vazquez case, and others], 1572, 1585 August; 2 leaves and 1 bifolium: paper; various sizes (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Incomplete set of documents relating to the case of Sebastian Bazquez [Vazquez], who claimed ownership of indigenous land. Includes unrelated material, such as Nahuatl petitions. Text in both Nahuatl and Spanish.
  - [Martín Cortés vs. Hernando de Paz], 1575 January 25 - February 11; 12 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Documents relating to the suit of Don Martín Cortés, Marqués del Valle, versus Hernando de Paz over the estancia of Acatlán. Cover page indicates the documents contain the "probanzas y testimonios" of the case. Case file begins with the original decision.
  - [Dowry of Catalina de Arellano], 1582 September 6; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Incomplete copy of the dowry of Doña Catalina de Arellano, in her marriage to Francisco de Terrazas, encomendero of Tulancingo (and Jaltepec?); no date given for transcription; Arellano received 22,000 gold pesos.
  - [Pedro de Ontiveros vs. debtors], 1582 September 15 - 1586 June 2; 12 leaves: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Documents relating to Pedro de Ontiveros' demand that indigenous men fully repay the 100 pesos he loaned them, of which he had only received half. Text mainly in Spanish and includes an admittance of debt (conocimiento) in Nahuatl, partially on one leaf.
  - [Pedro Gonzales de Paredes vs. debtors], 1587 November 20 - 1588 May 9; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Indigenous men promised to repay Pedro Gonzales de Paredes 17 fánegas of maize for a monetary loan; Paredes successfully litigated to force payment. Text in Nahuatl and Spanish.
  - [Francisco de Terrazas vs. Diego Suares de Peredo], 1589 July 31 - 1590 March 15; 4 bifolia: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Case documents relating to Francisco de Terrazas, encomendero of Tulancingo, who charged Diego de Suares de Peredo with the theft of six colts. Includes documents that do not relate directly to the case but do refer to Terrazas.
  - [Juan Cuetlachcohuacatl vs. Marcos de Torres], 1595 October 15 - 1596 November 22; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    A dispute between Juan Cuetlachcohuacatl and Marcos de Torres, trustee for the estate of Don Diego Alexandrino, over the ownership of a piece of land. File includes witness testimonies. Text in Spanish, with one document in Nahuatl.
  - [Notice of bail for Gabriel Bazquez and Don Juan Lorenço de San Francisco], 1600 January 4; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Two indigenous officials, Don Gabriel Bazquez and Don Juan Lorenço de San Francisco were in jail for non- payment of tribute; they were later freed on bail (fianzas). Text in Nahuatl and Spanish.
  - [Gomes Family land titles], 1626 April - 1718 August 7; 30 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Collection of documents concerning the Gomes family landholdings. The majority of the leaves (19) are records of land sales in Nahuatl, the rest are in Spanish. (FF.20-1 are transcribed and translated in Lockhart 1991, pp. 97-101).
  - [Estate of Pedro de la Mora and Doña Felipa de Arteaga], ca. 1634 - 1641; 142 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Compilation of documents relating to the estate of Pedro de la Mora and Doña Felipa de Arteaga. Their daughter Doña Maria Ordoñez petitioned her uncle Andres de la Mora for the release of these papers so the possessions could be divided amongst the heirs
  - [Bernardina Gutierrez vs. Domingo Hernandez], 1636 October 29 - 1637 May 30; 9 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Documents regarding a dispute between Bernardina Gutierrez and her son, Domingo Hernandez, over an hacienda which she had rented out to him. Gutierrez wants the hacienda back, and livestock and pesos owed. Text in Spanish with a testimony in Nahuatl and Spanish.
  - [Juan Cordero vs. Francisco de Carrion], 1641 September 6 - 13; 1 bifolium: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    A provision from the Real Audiencia in the case entitled Juan Cordero versus Francisco de Carrion involving the possession of 45 mules. With the official seal and signatures of the oidores.
  - [Sale and transfer of titles for Indigenous land], 1642 May 2 - 1643 September 8; 3 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Documents relating to the sale and transfer of ownership of land between four indigenous owners: Gaspar de Santiago, Diego de Mendosa, Juan de Ayala and Francisco Lario Gomez. Two leaves are in Nahuatl, one leaf in Spanish.
  - [Diego Lopez de Escobar vs. Antonio de Mendoça], 1643 November 21 - December 19; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Provision from the Real Audiencia. Diego Lopez de Escobar was the guardian ad litem for the children of Juan Vibaldo [Bibaldo] de Mirabal and Ynes de Escobar, both deceased. The court ruled against Antonio de Mendoça.
  - [Documents relating to the estate of Don Juan Manuel Basquez, and others], 1644 April 18 - 1777 April 9; 30 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Doña Josepha Catharina Franco, widow of Don Juan Manuel Basquez, initiated litigation to settle debts owed to her deceased husband. File includes a list of debtors, acknowledgements of debt, and documents relating to the landholdings of Luis Santos.
  - [Francisco Ordoñez and Cathalina Dominguez vs. Miguel Caro], 1645 July 10 - 15; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Provision from the Real Audiencia concerning the criminal case of Francisco Ordoñez and his wife Cathalina Dominguez versus Miguel Caro. Caro was found guilty of assaulting Cathalina; he was sentenced and paid his bail.
  - [Juan de Olibares vs. Domingo Hernandes Yañes and Dyego Hortiz de Zanabria], 1646 February 27-28; 2 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Domingo Hernandes Yañes and Dyego Hortiz de Zanabria were jailed in a dispute over the ownership and payment of mules with Juan de Olibares, a resident of Tlaxcala City. Dr. Luis Ximenez, professor of the Royal University, advised them.
  - [Ana Gomes Montte Agudo vs. Juan Sanches de Montoya], 1660 July 27-29; 1 bifolium: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Provision from the Real Audiencia. Ana Gomes Montte Agudo was in a dispute with Juan Sanches de Montoya, a local merchant, over her deceased husband's debt. With the official seal and signatures of the oidores.
  - [Compilation of petitions, and Will of Ysabel Clara], 1664 April 30 - August 19; 12 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Varied and colorful collection of petitions presented to the alcalde mayor. Includes cases involving local merchants, a land dispute, a rape allegation, and the abduction of a wife. Issues concern both indigenous and Spanish residents.
  - [Mill of Santiago], 1675 November 5 - 7; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Document concerning the mill of Santiago (Molino de Santiago) in Tulantepec.
  - [Inventory of the estate of Phelipe de Baños], 1713 October 9; 2 bifolia: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Estate inventory indicating the monetary values of Baños' personal property, including houses on a hacienda named Guaxomulco. Prepared by Francisco de Medel, a local merchant.
  - [Doña Sebastiana de Yslas vs. Manzano de Aguilera], 1714 June 13 - 1724 May 29; 3 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Petition by Doña Sebastiana de Yslas demanding repyament of a loan borrowed by Pedro Manzano de Aguilera of San Miguel Huatengo.
  - Declaracion en favor de Maria Augustina de la Cruz, de Temascatitla, 1720 July 30; 2 bifolia: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Two copies of an original document in Nahuatl; one was transcribed from the original Nahuatl ca. 1722 - 1723; the other is a translation into Spanish made in 1777. The text contains an indigenous cabildo's confirmation about a plot of land.
  - [Dispute regarding Hacienda of Ixtlahuacan], 1720 December 6 - 1721 November 19; 38 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Documents relating to a dispute of ownership over a hacienda named Ysptlaguacan [Ixtlahuacan]. Property belonged to Francisco Lopez de Medina, and was inherited by his children, Cristobal Hernandes and Clara de Fonseca. Antonio de Espinosa, a resident o
  - [Regulations concerning the celebration of Corpus Christi], 1749 May 29; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Don Blas Perez de las Casas (secretary of the Inquisition and alcalde mayor) mandated that residents attend the procession of the sacrament of Corpus Christi. He also imposed a fine of wax for those who do not attend.
  - [Indigenous elections in Singuilucan], 1749 December 4 - 24; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Don Blas Perez de las Casas (secretary of the Inquisition and alcalde mayor) mandated that the indigenous residents of Singuilucan hold elections for posts in their local government. De las Casas proposed three candidates and rules for the election.
  - [Maria Cortes de Arellanos vs. Francisco de la Cruz], 1750 January 13 - 17; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Francisco de la Cruz (indigenous) was accused of having pre-marital relations with Maria Cortes de Arellanos. Cruz was jailed and implicated another man, Juan Thomas Thelles. File contains the testimony of both Thelles and Arellanos.
  - [Notice of visit from Don Blas Perez de las Casas], 1750 April 17 - May 3; 3 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Don Blas Perez de las Casas (secretary of the Inquisition and alcalde mayor) mandated that local leaders inform and prepare the indigenous people for his visit. He intended to register them, their wives, children and other relatives.
  - [Power of representation granted to Don Joachin Doistua], 1750 November 14; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Doña Luganda Fernandez de la Quintana, of Real del Monte, grants power of representation to Don Joachin Doistua, domicile priest.
  - [Notice about loose pigs], 1753 June 23; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Local indigenous people brought a complaint about the town's loose pigs, which were damaging their crops. All owners of such livestock were mandated to collect and tie them up.
  - [Benito Fernandez vs. Carlos Joachin Marquez de Figueroa], 1754 March 12; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    A provision from the Real Audiencia regarding litigation over a rancho. Dispute was between Don Benito Fernandez, custodian of Don Jose Lopez Lacaño, and Don Carlos Joachin Marquez de Figueroa, a local priest.
  - [Decision in the case of Francisco Xauier de Medina y Aguirre and the chaplaincy of Don Ygnacio de Castro], 1756 May 7 - 14; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Provision from the Real Audiencia. Don Francisco Xauier de Medina y Aguirre, administrator of the chaplaincy of Don Ygnacio de Castro, presented litigation to expedite the allocation of resources to establish the chaplaincy, as provided for in his will.
  - [Juan Family litigation regarding the title for Texalpan, and Will of Don Francisco Larios], 1758 March 11 - 1803 July 23; 36 leaves: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    The family of Don Christobal Juan, indigenous nobleman, lost an important family document, a bill of sale for a piece of land in Acatlán called Texalpan. He presented litigation to confirm his ownership of the property.
  - [Doña Juana de Bargas Machuca vs. Santiago Joseph de Galicia], ca. 1763 - 1764 September 20; 12 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Documents relating to the dispute between the aged widow Doña Juana de Bargas Machuca and the indigenous man Don Santiago Joseph de Galicia. Dispute pertains to an apple orchard and includes witness testimonies. Text in Spanish, with one document in Nahuatl.
  - [Don Pascual Monter vs. Andres Monter], 1763 September 27; 5 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Don Pascual Monter and Doña Maria de Escamilla issued a formal complaint against Andres Monter alleging that he committed incest by taking their daughter's virginity (Maria Rita Monter), and stole some of her valuables. Includes the testimony of Maria Rita Monter.
  - [Report on the production of saltpeter and gunpowder], 1764 January 14; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Report-testimony by Don Francisco de Borja y Victoria of the Santa Hermandad concerning the manufacture of saltpeter and gunpowder, and what could be done to augment its production.
  - [Indigenous governor of Atotonilco vs. the inheritors of Miguel Sanchez de Naua], 1764 October 9 - November 19; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Indigenous governor of Atotonilco denounced the inheritors of Miguel Sanchez de Naua [Nava?] who took over indigenous community lands. The Real Audiencia condemned the illicit removal and restored the lands.
  - [Will of Domingo de la Cruz, and Statement on the death of Domingo Rosales], 1768 March 1 - September 12; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Will of Domingo de la Cruz including text relating to the death of an indigenous man, Domingo Rosales. Will in Nahuatl, with other text in Spanish.
  - [Litigation converning parochial rights], 1769 April 2 - 1796 June 18; 56 leaves: paper; 32 x 23 cm. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Documents relating to a priest's abuse of privileges with the local clergy. He allegedly took advantage of his powers to levy tariffs (arancel) and made the people do his personal work. Several complaints by the indigenous cabildo prompted this legal act.
  - [Tribute payment relief], 1772 December 23 - 1773 May; 4 leaves: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    The Real Acuerdo in Mexico City response to a plea by the indigenous people of Acaxochitlán who petitioned for relief of tribute payment because of an epidemic which they were suffering.
  - [Inventory of the estate of Doña Ysabel de Alfaro], 1774 February 21; 2 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Partial inventory of the personal effects of Doña Ysabel de Alfaro, deceased. Page 92 is an assessment of her china and crystal ware which reveals material culture for this period. Page 93 lists and describes her religious images.
  - [Broadside], 1774 October 18; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Broadside announcement. On recto: record of a land sale by Luis José Casares to his cousin; record ordering a new election for indigenous leadership positions, with a list of names (possibly candidates). Broadside text in Nahuatl; writing on recto in Spanish.
  - [Complaint of María de Ortega], 1776 June 4 to 7; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Formal complaint by María de Ortega against Manuel de Ybarra over a broken marriage promise. Ybarra had proposed to Ortega but after eight months they still had not married.
  - [Don Manuel Monter vs. Don Jose Ygnacio Asiain], 1776 November 19 - 1796 April 11; 12 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Documents concerning Don Manuel Monter of Rancho de Tiltepec, el Chico. Monter sought to collect payment from various neighbors who were indebted to him. In particular, he brought litigation against Don Jose Ygnacio Asiain for the amount of $110 pesos.
  - Ymbentario á los bienes q[u]e quedaron p[o]r fallecimiento del intestado D. Sebastian Farias vecino de este Pueblo, ca. 1781 - 1834 August 4; 111 leaves and 1 bifolium: paper; various sizes (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Title translates as: "Inventory of the estate of Don Sebastián Farías, who died without a testament, and was a resident of this town." Farias died without a will, and the documents represent the lengthy settlement of his estate, including inventories.
  - [Estate of Doña Maria Antonia de Órdaz], 1784 December 11 - 1789 June 3; 13 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Documents for the estate of Doña Maria Antonia de Órdaz, wife of Don Estevan Garcia. Don José Perez de Arroyo y Roxas de Sandoval was the accountant in charge of the inventory and distribution of the inheritance to her two children.
  - [Litigation over water rights], 1785 December 1 - 1786 March 16; 6 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Dispute over water rights in Atotonilco el Grande. Hacienda de la Venta, which belonged to the Conde de Santiago, claimed ownership of water supplies, and indigenous leaders protested. Includes testimony of Don Nicolas Montalvo.
  - [Notice from the Viceroy regarding infantry deserters], 1788 July 3; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Broadside announcement: The Viceroy disapproved of dissention from the infantry regiments and mandated that deserters be punished severely.
  - [Letters from Don Bernardo Bonavía], 1789 March 16 - 1791 March 26; 7 leaves: paper; various sizes (Box 2, Folder 25)
    A small collection of brief letters from Don Bernardo Bonavía, Intendant of Mexico, to the subdelegate of Tulancingo. Letters consist mostly of instructions and orders, often dealing with viceregal mandates.
  - [Record of baptisms, marriages and burials], 179-?; 1 leaf: paper; 16 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Small fragment sheet which lists the number of baptisms, marriages and burials in Tulancingo and its dependencies. Verso has a comment about corn. Undated.
  - [Census regulations], 1790 March 10; 4 leaves: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    A list of rules and regulations from Don Bernardo Bonavía for conducting the census (padron). There are 19 detailed paragraphs of instructions.
  - [Letter to Don Bernardo Bonavía], 1791 August 20; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Unsigned copy of a letter to Don Bernardo Bonavía, Intendant of Mexico, concerning the status of the census (padron).
  - [Prohibition against playing games], 1792 October 25; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)